Guidelines for facilitating meetings.
So it seems pretty easy and obvious,
but it's very important.
That's why we're covering it in detail.
We as project managers facilitate meetings
all the time.
We've got to get the people within the
meeting to come to some type of conclusion.
Otherwise, we're just yapping.
Okay, so guidelines for facilitating
meetings on the second slide.
We need to ensure the meeting is an
appropriate use of time.
You don't have a meeting just to have a
meeting.
We create and distribute
an agenda prior to the
meeting, and we should
actually stick to the agenda.
So there's a reason for having the
meeting.
That's why we have an agenda.
We're going to let people know the purpose
of that meeting.
We only invite those who will actually add
value to the meeting.
Not just any old buddies should be in the
meetings.
All right.
So who needs to know something who's going
to do.
contribute to the meeting.
We'll start the meetings promptly.
And yep, support that sense of urgency.
You don't just go on for hours.
Some people like to yap all day long and
we all know some of those people.
Okay, but that isn't a good use of time.
It's not adding value
unless we're actually
accomplishing something or
discussing something of value.
All right.
We should review the agenda with the
participants.
Allow others to speak and share as
appropriate.
Doesn't always have to be us.
We have team members.
We have SMEs and we'll count on.
We need to know progress.
We need to know information or
recommendations, whatever the case is.
All right.
We should assign someone to take meeting
minutes.
I cannot tell you enough, CYA,
CYA, CYA.
Cover your assets, document.
make decisions are made in meetings and if
you don't document who made the decisions
what decisions were made when why that
will come back to haunt you later believe
me it's happened to me all right I was so
overworked I stopped taking meeting
minutes and of course the
inevitable happened I was
asked why are we doing
this Who said to Wadmabup?
I couldn't answer that question because I
did not document anymore.
Stupid, stupid, stupid.
So make sure you document those meeting
minutes.
Okay.
All right, let's look at the next one.
Keep discussions on topic.
Try to stick to the agenda.
Okay.
One thing can lead to another,
but then you get off topic and you can
talk, all of a sudden you're talking about
the football game or whatever.
I had nothing to do.
with our project meeting.
All right, recap the meeting with any
action items, things that need to be done,
adjourn the meeting when it's supposed to.
All right, end on time.
Everybody's time is valuable, including
yours.
All right, so we start on time,
stick to the agenda as much as possible
every now and then something new will come
up.
Finish as scheduled.
Distribute meeting.
minutes, whether it's on SharePoint or you
send out emails, whatever the case is,
remember decisions were made in those
meetings.
So take the meeting minutes, distribute
the meeting minutes.
Oh, so important that everybody is aware
of what decisions were made.
All right, four types of meeting
attendees.
This is the ESVP model.
So we have who are called explorers,
the ease, obviously.
These are people excited to be at the
meeting.
They're happy to be away from their desks
and their normal day-to-day work.
They want to learn and participate in the
meeting.
So they're excited to be there.
They want to be there.
Then we have shoppers.
They're happy if they learn one new
concept, get something new out of it.
Then we've got vacationers.
They're happy to be away from their
day-to-day work, they just want to change.
They are not necessarily
trying to get anything
out of the meeting, unlike the explorers.
Okay, so big difference there.
Then we have the peas, the prisoners.
These people are stuck there.
They have to be there.
Okay, so they act like prisoners.
Yep, they are against their will,
handcuffed, whatever they.
the case is.
All right.
So these are just types of meeting
attendees.
Remember, we've got 42% of the exams can
be about people.
So how we take meeting, hold meetings,
and the people who attend meetings,
you might want to know.